<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

DNSMessageParser is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
parses individual fields of DNS messages received in input tuples, 
and emits tuples containing message data.  
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.
The tuples contain individual fields from the input message, as
specified by output attribute assignments.  

The DNSMessageParser operator expects only DNS messages in its input tuples,
without any of the headers that precede them in network packets.  The
[PacketLiveSource] and [PacketFileSource] operators can produce tuples that contain
DNS messages with the PAYLOAD_DATA() output attribute assignment function.

The DNSMessageParser operator consumes input tuples containing DNS messages,
parses individual fields in the messages, 
selects messages to emit as output tuples with filter expressions,
and assigns values to them with output attribute assignment expressions.

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the DNSMessageParser operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|DNS parser result functions]

The DNSMessageParser operator emits a tuple on each output port for each input tuple,
optionally filtered by the 'outputFilters'
parameter.  Specified fields from the DNS message in the input tuple are assigned to output
attributes with the DNS parser result functions.
All attributes of all output ports must be assigned values, either with explicit
assignment expressions, or implicitly by copy from input tuples.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an application,
include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse::*;

# Threads

The DNSMessageParser runs on the thread of the upstream operator that sends
input tuples to it. It does not start any threads of its own.

# Exceptions

The DNSMessageParser operator will throw an exception and terminate in these
situations:

* No output ports are specified.

* The `outputFilters` parameter is specified, and the number of expressions 
specified does not match the number of output ports specified.

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

DNS messages and the fields they contain are described here:
  
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System]
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_DNS_record_types]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2308] for SOA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2872] for SRV resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3403] for NAPTR resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3596] for AAAA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4034] for DS, RRSIG, NSEC, and DNSKEY resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4408] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5155] for NSEC3 and NSEC3PARAM resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6891] for OPT resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7208] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7505] for MX resource records

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|DNS result functions].  

      </description>
      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description>   </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
      </libraryDependencies>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>

      <parameter>
        <name>messageAttribute</name>
        <description>

This required parameter specifies an input attribute of type `blob` that
contains a DNS message to be parsed by the operator.

        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Attribute</expressionMode>
        <type>blob</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which DNS
messages should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|DNS result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all DNS messages processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>processorAffinity</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes one expression of type `uint32` that specifies
which processor core the operator's thread will run on.  The maximum value is
*P-1*, where *P* is the number of processors on the machine where the operator
will run.

Where the operator runs on a thread of its own, this parameter applies to the
operator's thread.  This is the situation when the operator's input port is
configured as a threaded input port, and when the operator has an @parallel
annotation.

Where the operator runs on the thread of an upstream operator, this parameter
affects the thread of the operator that sends tuples to it. This is the
situation when the operator is fused with an upstream operator.

The default is to dispatch the operator's thread on any available processor.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>

      <inputPortSet>
        <description>

The DNSMessageParser operator requires one input port.  One input attribute must be
of type `blob` and must contain a DNS message, excluding the network headers that
proceed them in network packets, as specified by the required parameter
`messageAttribute`.

The PAYLOAD_DATA() output assignment function of the [PacketLiveSource] and
[PacketFileSource] operators produces attributes that
can be consumed by the DNSMessageParser operator.

        </description>
        <windowingDescription></windowingDescription>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>NonWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>Oblivious</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </inputPortSet>

    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>

      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The DNSMessageParser operator requires one or more output ports.

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each input tuple
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|DNS result functions].  
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Preserving</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>0</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
