<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

NetflowMessageParser is an operator for the IBM Streams product that 
parses individual fields of Netflow messages received in input tuples, 
and emits tuples containing message data.  
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.
The tuples contain individual fields from the input message, as
specified by output attribute assignments.  

The NetflowMessageParser operator expects only Netflow messages in its input tuples,
without any of the headers that precede them in network packets.  The
[PacketLiveSource] and [PacketFileSource] operators can produce tuples that contain
Netflow messages with the PAYLOAD_DATA() output attribute assignment function.

The NetflowMessageParser operator consumes input tuples containing Netflow messages,
parses indivdual fields in flow records within Netflow version 5 and version 9 messages, 
selects flows to emit as output tuples with filter expressions,
and assigns values to them with output attribute assignment expressions.

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the NetflowMessageParser operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|Netflow parser result functions]

For Netflow version 5 messages, there are result functions for each field in the
message header and flow records.  For Netflow version 9 messages, there are
result functions for each field in the message header and the standardized
fields in flow records.  Nonstandardized fields in flow records can be accessed
by field number.

The NetflowMessageParser operator emits a tuple on each output port for each flow
record within a Netflow version 5 or 9 message, optionally filtered by the 'outputFilters'
parameter.  Specified fields from each flow record are assigned to output
attributes with the Netflow parser result functions.
All attributes of all output ports must be assigned values, either with explicit
assignment expressions, or implicitly by copy from input tuples.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an application,
include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse::*;

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

Netflow version 5 messages and the fields they contain are described here:

* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035]
* [http://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/td/docs/net_mgmt/netflow_collection_engine/3-6/user/guide/format.html#wp1006108]

Netflow version 9 messages and the fields they contain are described here:
    
* [https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3954.txt]
* [http://www.iana.org/assignments/ipfix/ipfix.xhtml]
* [http://www.cisco.com/en/US/technologies/tk648/tk362/technologies_white_paper09186a00800a3db9.html]

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|Netflow result functions].  

      </description>
      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description>common code for toolkit operators</cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
      </libraryDependencies>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
      <parameter>
        <name>messageAttribute</name>
        <description>

This required parameter specifies an input attribute of type `blob` that
contains a Netflow message to be parsed by the operator.

        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Attribute</expressionMode>
        <type>blob</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>sourceAttribute</name>
        <description>


        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Attribute</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which Netflow
messages should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|Netflow result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all Netflow messages processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>processorAffinity</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes one expression of type `uint32` that specifies
which processor core the operator's thread will run on.  The maximum value is
*P-1*, where *P* is the number of processors on the machine where the operator
will run.

Where the operator runs on a thread of its own, this parameter applies to the
operator's thread.  This is the situation when the operator's input port is
configured as a threaded input port, and when the operator has an @parallel
annotation.

Where the operator runs on the thread of an upstream operator, this parameter
affects the thread of the operator that sends tuples to it. This is the
situation when the operator is fused with an upstream operator.

The default is to dispatch the operator's thread on any available processor.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
      <inputPortSet>
        <description>

The NetflowMessageParser operator requires one input port.  One input attribute must be
of type `blob` and must contain a Netflow message, excluding the network headers that
proceed them in network packets, as specified by the required parameter
`messageAttribute`.

The PAYLOAD_DATA() output assignment function of the [PacketLiveSource] and
[PacketFileSource] operators produces attributes that
can be consumed by the NetflowMessageParser operator.

        </description>
        <windowingDescription></windowingDescription>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>NonWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>Oblivious</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </inputPortSet>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The NetflowMessageParser operator requires one or more output ports.

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each input tuple
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.parse.html|Netflow result functions].  
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Preserving</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>0</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
