<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
    <description>

# introduction 

DNSPacketDPDKSource is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
captures live network packets from one of the network interfaces attached to the
machine where it executes. The operator function and structure are
similar to the PacketLiveSource and DNSMessageParser operators; 
see the documentation for those for details
of common functions and general background.  
The primary difference between
these related operators is that DNSPacketDPDKSource leverages 
the [http://www.dpdk.org|data plane development kit (DPDK)]
for higher performance.

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the PacketFileSource operator:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|network header parser result functions]

The DNSPacketDPDKSource operator steps quietly over 'jmirror' headers prepended to packets
by Juniper Networks 'mirror encapsulation'.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an
application, include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns::*;


# promiscuous mode 

Ethernet interfaces normally ignore packets that are not addressed to them.
However, when 'promiscious' mode is enabled, they can
capture all network packets on their ethernet segment, even those that are not
addressed to them.  This is sometimes referred to as 'network sniffing'.  
However, modern ethernet routers normally send only packets that are
addressed to the ethernet device; 'promiscious' mode is useful only when a switch has been
specifically configured to send packets to an ethernet interface that are not
addressed to it. This is sometimes referred to as 'mirroring'.

The DNSPacketDPDKSource operator will enable 'promiscuous' mode in a ethernet
interface when its 'promiscous' parameter is set to `true`.


# hardware dependencies

DPDK supports a variety of [http://www.dpdk.org/doc/nics|ethernet devices]. 
The DNSPacketDPDKSource operator has been tested with these adapters:

* Mellanox ConnectX-3
* Mellanox ConnectX-3 Pro
* Intel e1000
* Intel I350

The [http://dpdk.org|DPDK libraries] must be compiled from source code and installed on the machine where
the network adapter is installed. Streams processing elements (PEs) must be placed
on this machine.

# software dependencies

DPDK depends upon additional Linux software packages, beyond those required for Streams.
In particular, it requires libraries that match the specific version of the kernel your machine uses.
To install these libraries, type these commands at a prompt:

    bash&gt; sudo yum install glibc-devel
    bash&gt; sudo yum install libibverbs-devel
    bash&gt; sudo yum install "kernel-devel-$(uname -r)"


# installing and configuring DPDK

The [http://dpdk.org/doc/guides/linux_gsg/index.html|DPDK user guide] has detailed instructions for
installing DPDK and configuring it for particular ethernet devices. These notes are a summary of those instructions.
They include many Linux commands that should be entered at a command prompt in a Terminal window.
In the instructions below, these commands are prefixed with 'bash&gt;'.
Many of the commands require 'root' privileges; they are prefixed with 'bash&gt; sudo'.


*identify ethernet device and network interface*

Your machine probably has multiple ethernet interfaces.
To configure the DPDK device driver, you will need to specify which ethernet device
you intend to use with DPDK, 
and which Linux network interface is assigned to it.

First, display a list of ethernet devices installed in your machine by typing this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; lspci | grep ethernet
    0002:01:00.0 Ethernet controller: Mellanox Technologies MT27520 Family [ConnectX-3 Pro]
    0003:05:00.0 Ethernet controller: Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme BCM5719 Gigabit Ethernet PCIe (rev 01)
    0003:05:00.1 Ethernet controller: Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme BCM5719 Gigabit Ethernet PCIe (rev 01)
    0003:05:00.2 Ethernet controller: Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme BCM5719 Gigabit Ethernet PCIe (rev 01)
    0003:05:00.3 Ethernet controller: Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme BCM5719 Gigabit Ethernet PCIe (rev 01)
    0005:01:00.0 Ethernet controller: Mellanox Technologies MT27520 Family [ConnectX-3 Pro]

If none of the supported ethernet devices listed above is displayed, the DNSPacketDPDKSource operator is not supported.

Otherwise, note the numbers preceding the word 'Ethernet' for the device you intend to use with DPDK.
These numbers are the PCI 'bus:slot.function' address of the device: 
they identify the PCI bus the device uses,
the physical slot the device is installed in, 
and the function number (the port number, for cards with multiple ethernet ports).

Then, display a list of Linux network interfaces, and the ethernet devices they are assigned to, by typing this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; ls -la /sys/class/net
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP2p1s0 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0002:00/0002:00:00.0/0002:01:00.0/net/enP2p1s0
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP2p1s0d1 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0002:00/0002:00:00.0/0002:01:00.0/net/enP2p1s0d1
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP3p5s0f0 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0003:00/0003:00:00.0/0003:01:00.0/0003:02:09.0/0003:05:00.0/net/enP3p5s0f0
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP3p5s0f1 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0003:00/0003:00:00.0/0003:01:00.0/0003:02:09.0/0003:05:00.1/net/enP3p5s0f1
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP3p5s0f2 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0003:00/0003:00:00.0/0003:01:00.0/0003:02:09.0/0003:05:00.2/net/enP3p5s0f2
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP3p5s0f3 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0003:00/0003:00:00.0/0003:01:00.0/0003:02:09.0/0003:05:00.3/net/enP3p5s0f3
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP5p1s0 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0005:00/0005:00:00.0/0005:01:00.0/net/enP5p1s0
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 enP5p1s0d1 -&gt; ../../devices/pci0005:00/0005:00:00.0/0005:01:00.0/net/enP5p1s0d1
    lrwxrwxrwx.  1 root root 0 Sep 28 09:49 lo -&gt; ../../devices/virtual/net/lo

Find the Linux network interface of your ethernet device by matching its PCI 'bus:slot:function' address to those listed, preding the string '/net/'.

For example, the 'lspci' list shows two Mellanox ethernet devices with PCI addresses '0002:01:00.0' and '0005:01:00.0'. 
The 'ls' list shows the adapters are assigned to network interfaces 'enP2p1s0' and 'enP5p1s0', respectively.

Note the PCI 'bus:slot.function' address and Linux network interface of the ethernet device you intend to use with DPDK.
You will need these values in subsequent steps.


*create Linux user group for DPDK*

DPDK will lock the memory pages containing its buffers to prevent the kernel from swapping them out to disk while it is using them.
Users who run the DNSPacketDPDKSource operator will need permission to do this.

To grant this permission, create a Linux user group for DPDK and add the user accounts that will run the DNSPacketDPDKSource operator to the group.

For example, to create a Linux user group 'dpdk' and add your own user account to it, open a Terminal window and type these commands at the prompt:

    bash&gt; sudo groupadd dpdk
    bash&gt; sudo usermod -a -G dpdk $USER

To verify that your user account is in the 'dpdk' group, type this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; groups $USER
    streamsdpdk : streamsdpdk dpdk

To grant permission to lock memory pages, edit the '/etc/security/limits.conf' system file:

    bash&gt; sudo vi /etc/security/limits.conf

 and insert this line into the 'limits.conf' file:

    \@dpdk - memlock unlimited


*prepare Linux user account for DPDK*

You will need some environment variables whenever you use DPDK.
To set these variables permanently, edit the '$HOME/.bashrc' script by typing this at a command prompt:

    vi $HOME/.bashrc

and insert these lines into the '.bashrc' file, 
substituting the Linux network interface and
PCI 'bus:slot.function' address of the ethernet device you intend to use with DPDK:

    export RTE_SDK=$HOME/dpdk-2.2.0
    [[ $( uname -m ) == "x86_64" ]] &amp;&amp; export RTE_TARGET=x86_64-native-linuxapp-gcc
    [[ $( uname -m ) == "ppc64le" ]] &amp;&amp; export RTE_TARGET=ppc_64-power8-linuxapp-gcc
    export DPDK_INTERFACE=network-interface-name
    export DPDK_DEVICE=ethernet-device-address


*log off and log back on*

After creating the 'dpdk' user group and making the changes to $HOME/.bashrc described above, 
log off your user account and log back in to put the changes into effect.


*configure Linux 'hugepages'*

DPDK uses [https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/vm/hugetlbpage.txt|Linux kernel 'hugepages' support] 
to allocate large buffers with minimal 'translation lookaside buffer (TLB)' overhead.
The size and number of 'hugepages' available for DPDK must be configured in the Linux kernel. 
This requires 'root' access, and may require rebooting the machine.

Note that the memory allocated for hugepages will reduce the memory available for Streams and other applications.

To display the amount of memory installed in your machine, and the amount of memory available, type this at a a command prompt:

    bash&gt; cat /proc/meminfo | grep -i mem
    MemTotal:       263636096 kB
    MemFree:        226797632 kB
    MemAvailable:   249287680 kB
    Shmem:            131776 kB

To display the size and number of hugepages currently allocated, type this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; cat /proc/meminfo | grep -i hugepages
    AnonHugePages:         0 kB
    HugePages_Total:      10
    HugePages_Free:        0
    HugePages_Rsvd:        0
    HugePages_Surp:        0
    Hugepagesize:      16384 kB

The supported sizes of hugepages depend upon the machine architecture. 
Typical sizes for the architectures supported by IBM Streams include: 

* 4KB, 8KB, 64KB, 256KB, 1MB, 4MB, 16MB, or 256MB _... for 'x86_64' (x86_64 machines) ..._
* 4KB, 16MB, or 16GB _... for 'ppc64le' (Power8 little-endian machines) ..._

The size of hugepages on your machine is set by Linux kernel parameters when the machine is booted.
If you want to change the size of hugepages on your machine, please refer to these documents for details:

* https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/vm/hugetlbpage.txt
* https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/kernel-parameters.txt

The number of hugepages is determined by the 'vm.nr_hugepages' system control parameter.
This parameter can be set when the system is booted, and it can be changed later while the system is running.

For example, to set the 'vm.nr_hugepages' parameter to 10 when the system boots, edit the '/etc/sysctl.conf' system file and set the parameter like this:

    vm.nr_hugepages=10

To increase the 'vm.nr_hugepages' parameter to 1000 while the system is running, type this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; sudo sysctl -w vm.nr_hugepages=1000

To verify that the parameter has changed, type this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; sysctl vm.nr_hugepages
    vm.nr_hugepages = 1000

To verify that the number of hugepages has actually increased, type this at a command prompt:

    bash&gt; cat /proc/meminfo | grep -i hugepages
    AnonHugePages:         0 kB
    HugePages_Total:    1000
    HugePages_Free:        0
    HugePages_Rsvd:        0
    HugePages_Surp:        0
    Hugepagesize:      16384 kB

If the number of hugepages has not actually been increased to 1000, memory may be too fragemented.
In this case, you will need to reboot the machine and then increase the number of hugepages.

To make the hugepages accessible to the user accounts that will run the DNSPacketDPDKSource operator,
create and mount a directory for them by typing these commands at a prompt:

    bash&gt; sudo mkdir /dev/hugepages
    bash&gt; sudo mount -t hugetlbfs nodev /dev/hugepages -o gid=dpdk,mode=1770

To ensure the hugepages are mounted in the '/dev/hugepages' directory when the machine is rebooted, 
edit the '/etc/fstab' system file by typing this command at a prompt:

    bash&gt; sudo vi /etc/fstab

and inserting this line into the file:

    nodev  /dev/hugepages  hugetlbfs  gid=dpdk,mode=1770  0  0


*get DPDK library and utilities*

The DPDK source code needs to be downloaded,
configured for your machine's architecture and ethernet device,
and compiled into libraries and utilities.

First, download the DPDK source code and configure it for your machine's architecture
by typing these commands at a prompt:

    bash&gt; wget http://fast.dpdk.org/rel/dpdk-2.2.0.tar.xz
    bash&gt; tar -xvf dpdk-2.2.0.tar.xz
    bash&gt; cd $RTE_SDK
    bash&gt; make config T=$RTE_TARGET

Then, edit the DPDK configuration file by typing this command:

    bash&gt; vi ./build/.config

and change these parameters in the '.config' file:

    CONFIG_RTE_BUILD_COMBINE_LIBS=y
    CONFIG_RTE_MAX_MEMSEG=1024

and, if your machine has a Mellanox ethernet device, change this parameter in the '.config' file, too:

    CONFIG_RTE_LIBRTE_MLX4_PMD=y 

Then, compile DPDK by typing this command at a prompt:

    bash&gt; EXTRA_CFLAGS=-fPIC make                
    bash&gt; EXTRA_CFLAGS=-fPIC make install T=$RTE_TARGET


*re-compile Streams network toolkit*

If you don't already have the Streams network toolkit, get it by typing these commands at a prompt:

    bash&gt; cd $HOME/git
    bash&gt; git clone git@github.com:ejpring/streamsx.network.git

In any case, you will need to compile the Streams DPDK glue library.
To do this, type these commands at a prompt:

    bash&gt; cd $HOME/git/streamsx.network
    bash&gt; ant


*more to come...*


# sample applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# references

The ethernet frame format is described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethernet_frame]

The ethernet header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://linux.die.net/include/net/ethernet.h]
* [http://linux.die.net/include/linux/if_ether.h]

The IPv4 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv4]
* [http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc791.txt]
* [http://linux.die.net/include/netinet/in.h]
* [http://linux.die.net/include/netinet/ip.h]

The IPv6 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6_packet]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2460]
* [http://linux.die.net/include/netinet/ip6.h]

The UDP header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_Datagram_Protocol]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc768]
* [http://linux.die.net/include/netinet/udp.h]

DNS messages and the fields they contain are described here:
  
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System]
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_DNS_record_types]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2308] for SOA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2872] for SRV resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3403] for NAPTR resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3596] for AAAA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4034] for DS, RRSIG, NSEC, and DNSKEY resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4408] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5155] for NSEC3 and NSEC3PARAM resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6891] for OPT resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7208] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7505] for MX resource records

The Juniper Networks 'jmirror' encapsulation header is described here:

* [http://wiki.wireshark.org/jmirror]

The Cisco Systems ''Encapsulated Remote Switch Port Analyzer (ERSPAN)' encapsulation headers are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-foschiano-erspan-00]

The 'Generic Route Encapsulation (GRE)' headers used by Cisco ERSPAN encapsulation are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2784]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1701]

The Linux `tcpdump` command is described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/8/tcpdump]

The Wireshark tools are described here:

* [http://www.wireshark.org/]

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|network header and DNS parser result functions].  

    </description>


    <metrics>
       <metric>
          <name>nPacketsReceivedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts the number of packets received by the network interface,
as counted by DPDK.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
       </metric>

       <metric>
          <name>nPacketsDroppedCurrent</name>
          <description>
	  
This metric counts the number of packets dropped by the network interface,
as counted by DPDK.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
       </metric>

       <metric>
          <name>nPacketsProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>
	  
This metric counts number of bytes of packet data processed by the
operator.
	  
	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
       </metric>

       <metric>
          <name>nBytesProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of bytes of packet data processed by the
operator.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
       </metric>
    </metrics>

      <libraryDependencies>
	<library>
	<cmn:description>

General support functions.

	</cmn:description>
	<cmn:managedLibrary>
	<cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
	</cmn:managedLibrary>
	</library>

	<library>
	<cmn:description>
	
streams_source interface library to dpdk.
	
	</cmn:description>
	<cmn:managedLibrary>
	<cmn:lib>streams_source</cmn:lib>
	<cmn:libPath>../../impl/src/source/dpdk/build/lib</cmn:libPath>
	<cmn:includePath>../../impl/src/source/dpdk</cmn:includePath>
	</cmn:managedLibrary>
	</library>

      </libraryDependencies>

      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>

    <parameters>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
    <parameter>
      <name>lcoreMaster</name>
      <description>

Logical core number to be used for the master DPDK thread.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>int32</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>lcore</name>
      <description>

Logical core number on which this operator will run.

      </description>
      <optional>false</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>int32</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>nicPort</name>
      <description>

NIC port of type uint32 which sources packets for this
operator instance.  Obtaining the proper mapping may require
use of multiple tools, and varies by NIC.  

Suggested tools to help identify NIC ports:

   \- ifconfig

   \- dpdk-\*/tools/dpdk_nic_bind.py --status

   \- ibstat (for Mellanox NICs)

   \- lspci | grep -i net

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>int32</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>nicQueue</name>
      <description>

NIC queue of type int32 which sources packets for this operator instance.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>int32</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which packets
should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|DNSPacketDPDKSource result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all packets processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>promiscuous</name>
      <description> 

This optional parameter takes an expression of type 'boolean'
that specifies whether or not 'promiscuous' mode should be enabled on the
network interface.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>boolean</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>metricsInterval</name>
      <description>
     

This optional parameter takes an expression of type
`float64` that specifies the interval, in seconds, for sending operator
metrics to the Streams runtime. If the value is zero or less, the operator
will not report metrics to the runtime, and the output assigment functions
for `libpcap` statistics will be zero.

The default value is '10.0'.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>float64</type>
      <cardinality>1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The DNSPacketDPDKSource operator requires one or more output ports:

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each packet received
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified.

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|DNSPacketDPDKSource result functions].
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

	</description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Generating</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
	<allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
