<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

PacketFileSource is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
reads prerecorded network packets from 'packet capture (PCAP)' files, parses
the network headers, and emits tuples containing packet data.  
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.
The tuples may contain the entire packet, the
payload portion of the packet, or individual fields from the network headers, as
specified by output attribute assignments.  

The PacketFileSource operator expects PCAP files to contain complete ethernet
packets, starting with the ethernet header, including all protocol-specific
headers and the packet payload.  

The PacketFileSource operator 
selects packets to process with input filters,
parses individual fields in the packet's network headers, 
selects messages to emit as output tuples with output filter expressions,
and assigns values to them with output attribute assignment expressions.

Input filters are PCAP filter expressions, as described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the PacketFileSource operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|network header parser result functions]

The PacketFileSource operator recognizes these types of packet encapsulation, 
and steps quietly over their headers:

* Juniper Networks 'jmirror' encapsulation
* Cisco Systems 'Encapsulated Remote Switch Port Analyzer (ERSPAN)' encapsulation

Files containing complete ethernet packets can be created in PCAP format by a
variety of network diagnostic tools, such as the Linux `tcpdump` command and the
Wireshark open-source tools.

The PacketFileSource operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an
application, include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.source::*;

# Dependencies

The PacketFileSource operator depends upon the Linux 'packet capture library
(libpcap)'.  The library must be installed on the machine where this operator
executes. It is available as an installable 'repository package (RPM)' from the
'base' RHEL and CentOS repositories.  It can be installed with administrator
tools such as 'yum'.  This requires root privileges, which can be acquired
temporarily with administrator tools such as 'sudo'.

To install `libpcap`, enter this command at a Linux command prompt:

    sudo yum install libpcap-devel

Alternatively, you can download the source code for a newer version of `libpcap`
and build the library yourself. The new library can then be installed in system
directories, or used where built without being installed.

To do this, download the distribution package for the latest version of
`libpcap` from this address:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/]

To build `libpcap` from source code, open a 'terminal' window and type this at a
command prompt:

    cd .../directory
    tar -xvf .../libpcap-X.Y.Z.tar.gz
    cd .../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z
    ./configure
    make

To instruct the Streams compiler (that is, the 'sc' command) to use your version
of `libpcap` instead of the system version, set these environment variables
before compiling an application that contains the PacketLiveSource operator:

    export STREAMS_ADAPTERS_LIBPCAP_INCLUDEPATH=.../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z
    export STREAMS_ADAPTERS_LIBPCAP_LIBPATH=.../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z

For more information on configuring, building, and installing `libpcap`, refer
to its 'INSTALL.txt' file.

This operator has been tested with these versions of `libpcap`:

* libpcap 0.9.4, included in RHEL/CentOS 5.x
* libpcap 1.0.0, included in RHEL/CentOS 6.2
* libpcap 1.4.0, included in RHEL/CentOS 6.5
* libpcap 1.5.3, included in RHEL/CentOS 7.1
* libpcap 1.6.1
* libpcap 1.6.2
* libpcap 1.7.4
* libpcap 1.8.1

# Threads 

The PacketFileSource operator contains a separate thread for reporting its metrics to
the Streams runtime if the `metricsInterval` parameter is greater than zero.

When the PacketFileSource operator is configured without an input port, it
contains another thread which reads the PCAP file specified by the
`pcapFilename` operator.  When the operator reaches end-of-file, it terminates
the thread and terminates the operator.

# Exceptions 

The PacketFileSource operator will throw an exception and terminate in these situations:

* The `pcapFilename` parameter does not specify a valid PCAP recording.

* An input tuple's first parameter is not of type `rstring`, or does not specify a valid PCAP recording.

* The `inputFilter` and `outputFilters` parameters do not specify a valid PCAP filter expression.

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

The ethernet frame format is described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethernet_frame]

The IPv4 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv4]
* [http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc791.txt]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/ip]

The IPv6 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6_packet]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2460]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/ipv6]

The UDP header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_Datagram_Protocol]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc768]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/udp]

The TCP header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transmission_Control_Protocol]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc793]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/tcp]

The Juniper Networks 'jmirror' encapsulation header is described here:

* [http://wiki.wireshark.org/jmirror]

The Cisco Systems ''Encapsulated Remote Switch Port Analyzer (ERSPAN)' encapsulation headers are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-foschiano-erspan-00]

The 'Generic Route Encapsulation (GRE)' headers used by Cisco ERSPAN encapsulation are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2784]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1701]

The Linux `tcpdump` command is described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/8/tcpdump]

The Wireshark tools are described here:

* [http://www.wireshark.org/]

`libpcap` filter expressions, 
which are used with the `inputFilter` parameter, are described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|network header parser result functions].  

      </description>
      <metrics>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of packets processed by the operator.  When
an input filter is specified, this includes only packets that pass the
filter.

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nBytesProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of bytes of packet data processed by the
operator.  When an input filter is specified, this includes only packets
that pass the filter.

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
      </metrics>

      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description> </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:command>../../impl/bin/libpcapPath.pl</cmn:command>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
        <library>
          <cmn:description> </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_boost_filesystem</cmn:lib>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_boost_system</cmn:lib>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
      </libraryDependencies>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
      <parameter>
        <name>pcapFilename</name>
        <description>

This parameter takes an expression of type `rstring` that specifies the pathname
of a single input PCAP file for the operator to read. 

If the operator is
configured without an inport port, this parameter is required; if the operator
has an input port, this parameter is not allowed.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>inputFilter</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `rstring` that specifies
which input packets should be processed. The value of this string must be a
valid PCAP filter expression, as defined here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

The default value is an empty string, which
causes all packets read from the PCAP file to be processed.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which packets
should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|PacketFileSource result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all packets processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>initDelay</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `float64` that specifies the
number of seconds the operator will wait before it begins to produce tuples.

This parameter is allowed only when the `pcapFilename` parameter is also
specified.  

The default value is '0.0'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>processorAffinity</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `uint32` that specifies
which processor core the operator's thread will run on.  The maximum value is
*P-1*, where *P* is the number of processors on the machine where the operator
will run.
      
Where the operator runs on a thread of its own, this parameter applies to the
operator's thread.  This is the situation when the operator does not have an
input port (and the `pcapFilename` parameter is specified). This is also the
case when the operator has an input port, and it is configured as a threaded
input port, and when the operator has an @parallel annotation.
     
Where the operator runs on the thread of an upstream operator, this parameter
affects the thread of the operator that sends tuples to it. This is the
situation when the operator has an input port, and is fused with its upstream
operator.
      
The default is to dispatch the operator's thread on any available processor.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>jMirrorCheck</name>
      <description> 

This optional parameter takes an expression of type 'boolean'
that specifies whether or not the operator should check for Juniper Networks 'jMirror' headers on
packets, and step over them when found.

The default value is 'false'.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>boolean</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>metricsInterval</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `float64` that specifies the
interval, in seconds, for sending operator metrics to the Streams runtime. If
the value is zero or less, the operator will not report metrics to the runtime,
and the output assigment functions for `libpcap` statistics will be zero.
      
The default value is '10.0'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
      <inputPortSet>
        <description>

The PacketFileSource operator has one optional input port.

When the PacketFileSource operator is configured with an input port, the first
attribute must be of type `rstring`, and specifies the pathname of an input PCAP
file for the operator to read.

When the PacketFileSource operator is configured without an input port, the `pcapFilename`
parameter specifies the pathname of a single input PCAP file for the operator to
read.

The packets in a PCAP file may optionally be filtered as they are 
read from the file with
the `inputFilter` parameter.
The tuples produced by the operator may optionally be filtered
with the `outputFilter` parameter.

        </description>
        <windowingDescription></windowingDescription>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>NonWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>Oblivious</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>true</optional>
      </inputPortSet>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The PacketFileSource operator requires one or more output ports:

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each packet read from 
the PCAP file (and passed by the input filter, if the `inputFilter` parameter is specified)
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|PacketFileSource result functions].  
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

The PacketFileSource operator emits a punctuation marker on each output port
when it reaches the end of each input file.

        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Generating</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
