<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

PacketDPDKSource is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
receives network packets from a supported ethernet adapter. The operator function and structure are
similar to 
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/op$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source$PacketLiveSource.html|PacketLiveSource]; 
see that operator's documentation for details
of common functions and general background.  The primary difference between
these related operators is that PacketDPDKSource leverages the 
[http://www.dpdk.org|DPDK library] for higher performance.

DPDK supports a variety of [http://www.dpdk.org/doc/nics|ethernet adapters]. 
The PacketDPDKSource operator has been tested with these adapters:

* Mellanox ConnectX-3
* Mellanox ConnectX-3 Pro
* Intel e1000
* Intel I350

DPDK stores network packets received by a supported ethernet adapter in memory that is 
directly accessible by the PacketDPDKSource operator, bypassing the Linux kernel.
This reduces overhead and allows the PacketDPDKSource operator to ingest packets
at a higher rate than the PacketLiveSource operator. 
The PacketDPDKSource operator requires a dedicated processor core,
which must be specified explicitly, and which runs at 100% CPU utilization.

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions and any of these functions:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|network header parser result functions]

The PacketDPDKSource operator can be configured to step quietly over 'jmirror' headers prepended to packets
by Juniper Networks 'mirror encapsulation'.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an
application, include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.source::*;


# parallelization

DPDK can distribute network packets received by one ethernet adapter 
across multiple PacketDPDKSource operators. 
This can increase an application's packet rate by parallelizing its analytics.
Note that each PacketDPDKSource operator requires a separate processor core,
which runs at 100% CPU utiliziation.

DPDK requires that the total number of PacketDPDKSource operators be a power of 2,
that is, the total number of PacketDPDKSource operators must be 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16.
Packets received by the network adapter will be distributed across all of the operators,
which will run in parallel. 
Packets are distributed according to a hash of their source and destination addresses and ports,
so request and response packets that belong to the same TCP transaction are all sent to 
the same operator.


# promiscuous mode

Ethernet adapters normally ignore packets that are not addressed to them.
However, when 'promiscious' mode is enabled, and adapter can
capture all network packets on its ethernet segment, even those that are not
addressed to it.  This is sometimes referred to as &quot;network sniffing&quot;.  
However, ethernet switches normally send only packets that are
addressed to the adapter; 'promiscious' mode is useful only when a switch has been
specifically configured to send packets that are not
addressed to the adapter. This is sometimes referred to as &quot;mirroring&quot;.

The PacketDPDKSource operator will enable 'promiscuous' mode 
when its 'promiscous' parameter is set to `true`.


# setup for DPDK

The DPDK library requires some setup that is specific to the hardware and software configuration
of your machine. The notes below offer general guidelines for this setup, and examples for an
Intel processor with a Mellanox ethernet adapter. You will need to adapt the guidelines to match
your configuration.

You will need 'root' privileges for some steps below. They are indicated by the `sudo` command
in the examples.


**Linux dependencies**

DPDK depends upon additional Linux software packages, beyond those required for Streams.
In particular, it requires libraries that match the specific version of the Linux kernel.
To install these libraries, type these commands at a prompt:

    sudo yum install pciutils
    sudo yum install glibc-devel
    sudo yum install libibverbs-devel
    sudo yum install &quot;kernel-devel-$( uname -r )&quot;

If you will be using a Mellanox ethernet adapter, you will also need to
[http://www.mellanox.com/page/mlnx_ofed_matrix?mtag=linux_sw_drivers|download]
and
[http://dpdk.org/doc/guides/nics/mlx4.html|install] OFED drivers from Mellanox.


**gathering system information for DPDK**

To configure the PacketDPDKSource operator, you will need to know how many
processors the machine has, and how they are distributed amoung the machine's NUMA nodes.
Use this command to display that information:

    lscpu

You will also need the PCI bus address of the 
adapter, the Linux interface names of the adapter's ports, and the NUMA node number the adapter
is connected to.

For example, ind the PCI bus address of a Mellanox ethernet adapter with this command:

    /usr/sbin/lspci | grep -i mellanox | gawk '{print $1}'

To determine the Linux interface names of the adapter's ports, 
enter this command at a prompt:

    ls -l /sys/class/net | grep $DPDK_DEVICE | gawk '{print $9}'

and then, to determine the NUMA node number the adapter is connected to, 
enter this command at a prompt:

    cat /sys/class/net/$DPDK_INTERFACE/device/numa_node


**configuring a Linux user group for DPDK**

You will need a Linux user group for DPDK. To create the user group and add your own user account to it, 
enter these commands at a prompt:

    sudo groupadd dpdk
    sudo usermod -a -G dpdk $USER
    sudo cat &quot;@dpdk - memlock unlimited&quot; >/etc/security/limits.conf

You will need to log off and log back on for this to take effect. 
To verify that your user account is a member of the group, enter this command at a prompt:

    id

The PacketDPDKSource operator will need read/write permission for the Linux interface for the adapter's port. 
To grant that permission to all user accounts that are members of the 'dpdk' user group, 
enter these commands at a prompt:

    sudo chown root:dpdk /sys/class/infiniband/mlx4_0/device/net/$DPDK_INTERFACE/flags
    sudo chmod 666 /sys/class/infiniband/mlx4_0/device/net/$DPDK_INTERFACE/flags


**configuring Linux 'hugepages' for DPDK**

DPDK uses Linux 'hugepages' for its buffers. These buffers must be allocated in the memory connected to the 
same NUMA node as the ethernet adapter, and may use either 2MB or 1GB 'hugepages'. You must create mount
points for the 'hugepages' in the Linux file system and grant DPDK read/write permissions for them.

For example, to allocate 500 2MB 'hugepages' for DPDK buffers, enter these commands at a prompt:

    sudo mkdir /dev/hugepages-2MB 
    sudo mount -t hugetlbfs nodev /dev/hugepages-2MB -o pagesize=2MB
    sudo chmod 770 /dev/hugepages-2MB
    sudo chown root:dpdk /dev/hugepages-2MB
    sudo /usr/bin/bash -c &quot;echo 500 > /sys/devices/system/node/node$DPDK_NODE/hugepages/hugepages-2048kB/nr_hugepages&quot;

For another example, to allocate one 1GB 'hugepages' for DPDK buffers, enter these commands at a prompt:

    sudo mkdir /dev/hugepages-1GB 
    sudo mount -t hugetlbfs nodev /dev/hugepages-1GB -o pagesize=1GB 
    sudo chmod 770 /dev/hugepages-1GB
    sudo chown root:dpdk /dev/hugepages-1GB
    sudo /usr/bin/bash -c &quot;echo 1 > /sys/devices/system/node/node$DPDK_NODE/hugepages/hugepages-1048576kB/nr_hugepages&quot;

To verify that 'hugepages' have been allocated, enter this command at a prompt:

    grep -i -h hugepages /sys/devices/system/node/node*/meminfo


**setting environment variables for DPDK**

DPDK requires several environment variables. 
To set them, enter these commands at a prompt, or append them to your $HOME/.bashrc script:

    export RTE_SDK=$HOME/dpdk-17.02.1
    [[ $( uname -m ) == &quot;x86_64&quot; ]] &amp;&amp; export RTE_TARGET=x86_64-native-linuxapp-gcc
    [[ $( uname -m ) == &quot;ppc64le&quot; ]] &amp;&amp; export RTE_TARGET=ppc_64-power8-linuxapp-gcc
    [[ -x /usr/sbin/lspci ]] &amp;&amp; export DPDK_DEVICE=$( /usr/sbin/lspci | grep -i mellanox | gawk '{print $1}' )
    [[ -n $DPDK_DEVICE ]] &amp;&amp; export DPDK_INTERFACES=( $( ls -l /sys/class/net | grep $DPDK_DEVICE | gawk '{print $9}' ) )
    [[ -n $DPDK_INTERFACES ]] &amp;&amp; export DPDK_INTERFACE=${DPDK_INTERFACES[0]}

After adding these commands to your $HOME/.bashrc file, 
you will need to log off and log back on for them to take effect. 
To verify that the environment variables are set, enter this command at a prompt:

    export | grep -E 'RTE_|DPDK_'


**installing the DPDK library**

The PacketDPDKSource operator depends upon DPDK library version 17.02.1, available from
[http://dpdk.org]. The library must be configured for your machine and ethernet adapter,
and compiled from source code.

To get the DPDK source code, enter these lines at a command prompt:

    mkdir -p $RTE_SDK
    wget http://fast.dpdk.org/rel/dpdk-17.02.1.tar.xz
    tar -x -v -f dpdk-17.02.1.tar.xz -C $RTE_SDK --strip-components=1

To configure DPDK for your machine, enter these lines at a command prompt:

    cd $RTE_SDK
    make config T=$RTE_TARGET O=$RTE_TARGET

To configure DPDK for a Mellonox ethernet adapter, enter these lines at a command prompt:

    cd $RTE_SDK/$RTE_TARGET
    sed -i.bak s/CONFIG_RTE_BUILD_SHARED_LIB=./CONFIG_RTE_BUILD_SHARED_LIB=n/ ./.config
    sed -i.bak s/CONFIG_RTE_LIBRTE_MLX4_PMD=./CONFIG_RTE_LIBRTE_MLX4_PMD=y/ ./.config

To compile the DPDK source code into a library, enter these lines at a command prompt:

    cd $RTE_SDK/$RTE_TARGET
    EXTRA_CFLAGS=-fPIC make


**installing the Streams DPDK 'glue' library**

The PacketDPDKSource operator is part of the network toolkit for Streams,
which contains a 'glue' library for DPDK. 
To get the toolkit and compile the 'glue' library, enter these commands at a prompt:

    mkdir -p $HOME/git
    cd $HOME/git
    git clone git@github.com:IBMStreams/streamsx.network.git
    cd $HOME/git/streamsx.network
    ant toolkit
    EXTRA_CFLAGS=-fPIC ant dpdkglue


**compiling SPL applications with DPDK**

Streams SPL applications that include the PacketDPDKSource operator must be compiled with 
additional options for the GNU compiler and linker, like this:

    sc *streams-compiler-options* &quot;--cxx-flags=-fPIC -m64 -pthread -fopenmp&quot; &quot;--ld-flags=-Wl,-L -Wl,$RTE_SDK/$RTE_TARGET/lib -Wl,--no-as-needed -Wl,-export-dynamic -Wl,--whole-archive -Wl,-ldpdk -Wl,-libverbs -Wl,--start-group -Wl,-lrt -Wl,-lm -Wl,-ldl -Wl,--end-group -Wl,--no-whole-archive -Wl,-Map=app.map -Wl,--cref&quot; *other-streams-compiler-options*


**loose ends**

TODO: what kernel modules (besides ib_uverbs) need to be loaded for Mellanox devices?

TODO: can master thread run on the 'other' NUMA core ?

TODO: default for 'lcoreMaster' parameter is '-1' ... what does that mean?

TODO: what value should be specified for parameter 'nicPort'?

TODO: DPDK fails if only one PacketDPDKSource operator is configured!

TODO: DPDK fails if not executed as 'root'!

TODO: DPDK fails to allocate contiguous bufferspace when plenty is available!

TODO: DPDK hangs or throws exception on termination!

TODO: DPDK fails with 4.2, works with Streams 4.1!

    </description>
      <metrics>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsReceivedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts the number of packets received by the ethernet adapter, as counted by DPDK.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsDroppedCurrent</name>
          <description>
	  
This metric counts the number of packets dropped by the ethernet adapter, as counted by DPDK.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>
	  
This metric counts number of packets processed by the operator.
	  
	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nBytesProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of bytes of packet data processed by the operator.

	  </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
      </metrics>

      <libraryDependencies>

        <library>
          <cmn:description>
          Functions for parsing network headers.
	    </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

        <library>
          <cmn:description>
          Streams DPDK 'glue' library 'libstreams_source.a'.
	    </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_source</cmn:lib>
            <cmn:libPath>../../impl/src/source/dpdk/build/lib</cmn:libPath>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/src/source/dpdk/streams_source</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

      </libraryDependencies>

      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Never</providesSingleThreadedContext>

      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>

    </context>

    <parameters>

      <allowAny>false</allowAny>

      <parameter>
        <name>lcoreMaster</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter specifies a logical processor core for the DPDK master thread. 
This thread is not used for receiving packets, and does not have high CPU utiliztion.
If the machine has more than one NUMA node, specify a core on a node that does not
have the ethernet adapter connected to it. 

When multiple PacketDPDKSource operators are configured for the same ethernet adapter,
all operators must specify the same value with their 'lcoreMaster' parameters.

To determine how many processor cores your machine has, and which cores are connected to 
which NUMA nodes, execute the `lscpu` command at a Linux prompt.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>int32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>lcore</name>
        <description>

This required parameter specifies a logical processor core for the DPDK packet receive thread.
The core specified must belong to the NUMA node the ethernet adapter is connected to.
The receive thread will run the specified core at 100% CPU utilization.

If multiple PacketDPDKSource operators are configured for the same ethernet adapter,
each operator must specify a different value with its 'lcoreMaster' parameter. 
The total number of PacketDPDKSource operators must be a power of 2,
that is, the total number of PacketDPDKSource operators must be 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16.
Packets received by the network adapter will be distributed across all of the operators,
which will run in parallel.

To determine how many processor cores your machine has, and which cores are connected to 
which NUMA nodes, execute the `lscpu` command at a Linux prompt. 
To determine which NUMA node your ethernet adapter is connected to, look in the file
'/sys/class/net/$DPDK_INTERFACE/device/numa_node'.

      </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>int32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>nicPort</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter specifies which port of the ethernet adapter 
the operator will receive network packets from.
This applies only to adapters with multiple ports. 

The default value is '0' if this parameter is not specified.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>int32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>nicQueue</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter specifies which queue of received packets the operator will receive.
This applies only when multiple PacketDPDKSource operators are configured for the same ethernet adapter.
The value must be between 0 and 'N-1', where N is the total number of operators,
and each operator must specify a different queue, so that all queues are connected to an operator.

Note that DPDK requires the total number of queues and operators be a power of 2, that is,
the total number of queues and operators must be 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16.
DPDK will distribute packets across all of the queues, and therefore across all of the operators.

The default value is '0' if this parameter is not specified.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>int32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>buffersizes</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter specifies how much buffer space, in megabytes, 
to allocate from available 2MB Linux 'hugepages' for each NUMA node,
specified as a string containing comma-separated values. 
For the NUMA node the ethernet adapter is connected to, specify an even number of megabytes.
For other NUMA nodes, if any, specify zero.

For example, on a machine with one NUMA node,
specify "100" to allocate 100 megabytes of buffer space.
For another example, on a machine with two NUMA nodes, 
where the ethernet adapter is connected to the second node,
specify "0,100" to allocate 100 megabytes of buffer space on the second NUMA node.
If multiple PacketDPDKSource operators are configured for the same network adapter, 
all operators should specify the same values for their 'buffersizes' parameter.

To determine which NUMA node your ethernet adapter is connected to, enter the command
`cat /sys/class/net/$DPDK_INTERFACE/device/numa_node` at a Linux prompt.
To determine how much buffer space is available in the 'hugepages' for that NUMA node,
enter the command
`grep -i -h hugepages /sys/devices/system/node/node\*/meminfo`
at a Linux prompt.

If this parameter is not specified, 
DPDK will allocate all available 2MB Linux 'hugepages' for its buffer space.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>AttributeFree</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>promiscuous</name>
        <description> 

This optional parameter takes an expression of type 'boolean'
that specifies whether or not 'promiscuous' mode should be enabled on the
network interface.

The default value is 'false'.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>jMirrorCheck</name>
        <description> 

This optional parameter takes an expression of type 'boolean'
that specifies whether or not the operator should check for Juniper Networks 'jMirror' headers on
packets, and step over them when found.

The default value is 'false'.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which packets
should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|PacketDPDKSource result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all packets processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>metricsInterval</name>
        <description>
     
This optional parameter takes an expression of type
`float64` that specifies the interval, in seconds, for sending operator
metrics to the Streams runtime. If the value is zero or less, the operator
will not report metrics to the runtime, and the output assigment functions
for `libpcap` statistics will be zero.

The default value is '10.0'.

      </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    </parameters>

    <inputPorts/>

    <outputPorts>

      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The PacketDPDKSource operator requires one or more output ports:

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each packet received
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified.

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|PacketDPDKSource result functions].
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

	    </description>

        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Generating</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>

    </outputPorts>

  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
