<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>


PacketContentAssembler is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
reassembles application flows (such as SMTP, FTP, HTTP, and SIP)
and files (such as GIF, JPEG, HTML, and and PDF)
from raw network packets received in input tuples, 
and emits tuples containing the reassembled content. 
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.
The tuples contain individual fields from flows and files, as
specified by output attribute assignments.  

The PacketContentAssembler operator expects raw ethernet packets in its input tuples,
including all of their network headers.  The
[PacketLiveSource] and [PacketFileSource] operators can produce tuples that contain
DNS messages with the PACKET_DATA() output attribute assignment function.

The PacketContentAssembler operator 
consumes network packets from tuples received by its input port 
and reassembles flows and files in internal buffers.
It produces output tuples containing the results of its reassembly when
one of the following events is detected:

**FlowStart** The operator emits this event
whenever it detects the beginning of a 'flow' of packets.  A
'flow' is a sequence of related packets exchanged by a pair of network
endpoints, as identified by their addresses and port numbers, which are available
from result functions.  The flow is assigned a
unique identifier, which will be
used with all subsequent events related to the flow, allowing
downstream operators to correlate tuples related to the flow.

**FlowEnd** The operator emits this event
whenever it detects the end of a 'flow' of packets.  The
number of packets and bytes exchanged between the endpoints are
available from result functions. The flow's identifier will not be used again in any
subsequent event.

**FlowData** The operator emits this event  
with the payload data from packets related to a flow, excluding
the network headers, which is available from result functions.

**FlowTLS** The operator emits this event for flows that 
are encrypted with 'transport layer security (TLS)'.
The individual fields of the TLS headers and the encrypted data
are available from result functions.
Note that the toolkit does not have access to encryption
certificates, and cannot decrypt flow data.

**Request** The operator emits this event for flows that use a
'request/response' protocol (for example, SMTP, HTTP, or FTP),
after all request headers have been received. The URI and header values
are availble from result functions.

**Response** The operator emits this event for flows that use a
'request/response' protocol (for example, SMTP, HTTP, or FTP),
after all response headers have been received. The status and header values
are availble from result functions.

**FileChunk** The operator emits this event
whenever it finds a chunk of transaction data in an application 'file' format, that is,
a sequence of bytes in a format that could be stored
in a host file, and produced or consumed by an application (for
example, HTML, JPEG, or PDF).  The file is assigned a unique
identifier, which is used in all subsequent chunks of the same file.
Each chunk of the file is assigned a sequence number,
and the first and last chunks are flagged, so that 
a complete file can be reconstructed.
The MIME type from the 'ContentType' header specifies the type of file.

There is no necessary relationship between input tuples consumed and output tuples produced, that is,
the operator may consume one or more input tuples without producing any output tuples, or,
one input tuple consumed may produce one or more output tuples.

Output filters are SPL expressions that specify which events should produce output tuples on which output ports;
they must evaluate to a `boolean` value.
Output attribute assignments are also SPL expressions that assign values to the attributes of output tuples;
they must evaluate to the type of the attribute they assign to.
Output filters and attribute assignments may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the PacketContentAssembler operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.content.html|content assembler result functions]

Output tuple attributes that are not assigned a value explicitly, but which match
an input attribute in both name and type, will be copied automatically when the output tuple is produced.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an application,
include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.content::*;

# Dependencies

The PacketContentAssembler depends upon the 'Packet Analysis Module (PAM)'
library, developed by 
the IBM Internet Security (ISS) X-Force team, 
which is packaged separately from the toolkit.

The PAM library must be downloaded and installed separately from the toolkit.
When SPL applications containing the PacketContentAssembler operator are compiled,
the location of the installed PAM library must be specified with the STREAMS_ADAPTERS_ISS_PAM_DIRECTORY
environment variable. For example, before executing the `sc` command to compile such an application,
set the environment variable like this:

    export STREAMS_ADAPTERS_ISS_PAM_DIRECTORY=/home/username/com.ibm.iss.pam

# Threads

The PacketContentAssembler runs on the thread of the upstream operator that sends
input tuples to it.

# Exceptions

The PacketContentAssembler operator will throw an exception and terminate in these
situations:

* No output ports are specified.

* The `outputFilters` parameter is specified, and the number of expressions 
specified does not match the number of output ports specified.

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.content.html|content assembler result functions].  

      </description>
      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description></cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:command>../../impl/bin/libpamPath.pl</cmn:command>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
        <library>
          <cmn:description></cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
      </libraryDependencies>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Never</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>

      <parameter>
        <name>packetAttribute</name>
        <description>

This required parameter specifies an input
attribute of type 'blob' that contains an ethernet packet to be parsed
by the operator.

        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Attribute</expressionMode>
        <type>blob</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>timestampAttribute</name>
        <description>

This required parameter specifies an input
attribute of type 'float64' that contains the time, in seconds relative to the
begining of the Unix epoch (midnight on January 1st, 1970 in Greenwich, England)
when the packet was
originally received from an ethernet adapter.

        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Attribute</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>fileChunkSize</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter specifies a minimum size
for 'chunks' of file data provided via the assembler result functions.
This parameter may improve
performance by packing file data that arrives in fragments into
fewer, but larger, tuples.  However, the value specified is not a
maximum or minimum size: the operator may emit tuples with more file
data (for example, when large packets are received) or less file data
(for example, when the last chunk is small).

The default value is 100 kilobytes (102,400 bytes).

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>false</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>maximumFilesPerFlow</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter limits the number of
concurrent open files per flow.  If specified, further files in the flow
will be ignored after the limit is reached, unless the flow closes some of
the files it has opened, until the flow ends.  When this parameter is not
specified, flows may open an unlimited number of files.  Note that each open
file requires a buffer, whose size is specified by the `fileChunkSize`
parameter, so the total amount of memory is unlimited.  Long-running flows
that open many files without closing any of them may exhaust the available
memory.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>false</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>pamLibrary</name>
        <description>

          This optional parameter is a pathname for the PAM library, a
          Linux shared object library which implements the packet assembly engine.
          If the pathname value specified is not absolute, then it is
          relative to the directory specified by the STREAMS_ADAPTERS_ISS_PAM_DIRECTORY
          environment variable at compile time.
          The default value is 'iss-pam1.so'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>false</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Constant</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>pamTuning</name>
        <description>
          
          This optional parameter is a comma-separated list of strings
          containing tuning values for the PAM library, specified as &quot;name=value&quot;.
          PAM tuning values are described in the file `tune.csv` in
          the directory specified by the STREAMS_ADAPTERS_ISS_PAM_DIRECTORY
          environment variable.

          The operator automatically applies these tuning values, in addition to those specified
          with this parameter:

    pam.sensor.type.hint=xpfshell
    pam.debug.fragroute=false

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>false</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>AttributeFree</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which events
should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[./tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.content.html|content assembler result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all events to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    </parameters>

    <inputPorts>
      <inputPortSet>
        <description>

The PacketContentAssembler operator requires one input port.  One input attribute must be
of type `blob` and must contain a raw ethernet packet, including the network headers that
proceed them in network packets, as specified by the required parameter
`packetAttribute`.

The PACKET_DATA() output assignment function of the [PacketLiveSource] and
[PacketFileSource] operators produces attributes that
can be consumed by the PacketContentAssembler operator.

        </description>
        <windowingDescription></windowingDescription>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>NonWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>Oblivious</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </inputPortSet>
    </inputPorts>

    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The PacketContentAssembler operator requires one or more output ports.

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each event
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
[./tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.content.html|content assembler result functions].  
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Preserving</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>0</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>

  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
