<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

DNSPacketLiveSource is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
captures live DNS packets from an ethernet interface,
parses their network headers and the fields of the DNS message, and emits
tuples containing packet data. 
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.
The tuples may contain the entire packet, the
payload portion of the packet, or individual fields from the network headers and DNS message, as
specified by output attribute assignments.  

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator 
reads raw network packets from an ethernet adapter,
selects DNS packets to process with an input filter,
parses individual fields in the packet's network headers and DNS message, 
selects messages to emit as output tuples with output filter expressions,
and assigns values to them with output attribute assignment expressions.

Input filters are PCAP filter expressions, as described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the PacketFileSource operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|network header parser result functions]

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator recognizes these types of packet encapsulation, 
and steps quietly over their headers:

* Juniper Networks 'jmirror' encapsulation
* Cisco Systems 'Encapsulated Remote Switch Port Analyzer (ERSPAN)' encapsulation

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an
application, include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns::*;

# Capabilities

The PacketLiveSource operator requires special privileges to receive 'raw' network packets from an ethernet interface.

On machines where 'extended file attributes' (see [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extended_file_attributes])
are enabled in the Linux kernel, these Linux capabilities should be granted to a PE that includes the 
PacketLiveSource operator:

* CAP_NET_RAW+eip
* CAP_NET_ADMIN+eip

Linux capabilities can only be granted to an executable that resides on a local disk volume such as /tmp.

For 'standalone' Streams applications (that is, SPL source files compiled with a
'standalone' configuration), the user must grant these capabilities to the
program before executing it. This requires 'root' privileges. To do this:

* the SPL source must be compiled with the '--static-link' option

* the 'application bundle' must be unpacked with the 'spl-app-info' command into a directory on a local disk volume such as /tmp

* Linux capabilities must be granted to the unbundled program with this command:
 
    sudo setcap 'CAP_NET_RAW+eip CAP_NET_ADMIN+eip' .../bin/standalone.exe

For 'distributed' Streams applications, (that is, SPL source files compiled with
a 'distributed' configuration), the Streams runtime must grant these capabilities to
the program before executing it. This requires 'root' privileges.  To do this:

* the Streams runtime must be installed as 'root'

* the Streams domain must be registered as a Linux system service

* the Streams instance must have the 'instance.canSetPeOSCapabilities=true' property

* the Streams instance must have the 'instance.runAsUser=$USER' property

* the Streams instance must have the 'instance.applicationBundlesPath=/tmp/...' property

* the SPL source must be compiled with the '--static-link' option

On machines where 'extended file attributes' are not enabled in the Linux kernel, 'standalone' PEs that include the PacketLiveSource operator can be executed with 'root' privileges like this:

    sudo STREAMS_INSTALL=$STREAMS_INSTALL .../bin/standalone.exe


# Promiscuous Mode

Network interfaces normally ignore packets that are not addressed to them.
However, when 'promiscious' mode is enabled on a network interface, it can
capture all network packets on its ethernet segment, even those that are not
addressed to it.  This is sometimes referred to as "network sniffing".  Modern
ethernet switches normally send network interfaces only packets that are
addressed to them; 'promiscious' mode is useful only when a switch has been
specifically configured to send packets to a network interface that are not
addressed to it. This is sometimes referred to as "mirroring".

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator will enable 'promiscuous' mode in a ethernet
interface when its 'promiscous' parameter is set to `true`.

# Dependencies

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator depends upon the Linux 'packet capture library
(libpcap)'.  The library must be installed on the machine where this operator
executes. It is available as an installable 'repository package (RPM)' from the
'base' RHEL and CentOS repositories.  It can be installed with administrator
tools such as 'yum'.  This requires root privileges, which can be acquired
temporarily with administrator tools such as 'sudo'.

To install `libpcap`, enter this command at a Linux command prompt:

    sudo yum install libpcap-devel

Alternatively, you can download the source code for a newer version of `libpcap`
and build the library yourself. The new library can then be installed in system
directories, or used where built without being installed.

To do this, download the distribution package for the latest version of
`libpcap` from this address:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/]

To build libpcap from source code, open a 'terminal' window and type this at a
command prompt:

    cd .../directory
    tar -xvf .../libpcap-X.Y.Z.tar.gz
    cd .../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z
    ./configure
    make

To instruct the Streams compiler (that is, the 'sc' command) to use your version
of `libpcap` instead of the system version, set these environment variables
before compiling an application that contains the DNSPacketLiveSource operator:

    export STREAMS_ADAPTERS_LIBPCAP_INCLUDEPATH=.../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z
    export STREAMS_ADAPTERS_LIBPCAP_LIBPATH=.../directory/libpcap-X.Y.Z

For more information on configuring, building, and installing `libpcap`, refer
to its 'INSTALL.txt' file.

This operator has been tested with these versions of `libpcap`:

* libpcap 0.9.4, included in RHEL/CentOS 5.x
* libpcap 1.0.0, included in RHEL/CentOS 6.2
* libpcap 1.4.0, included in RHEL/CentOS 6.5
* libpcap 1.5.3, included in RHEL/CentOS 7.1
* libpcap 1.6.1
* libpcap 1.6.2
* libpcap 1.7.4

# Tuning

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator is often used in applications that ingest packets
at very high rates.  In these situations, the rate may be limited by the size of
the Linux network buffers.  If so, you can increase the size of these buffers by
setting Linux network configuration parameters.  Note that root privileges are
required to do this.

You can display the current values of the ethernet and IP configuration
parameters by entering these commands at a Linux prompt:

    /sbin/sysctl net.core
    /sbin/sysctl net.ipv4

For example, these are typical default values for Linux configuration parameters
in RHEL/CentOS 5 and 6:

    net.core.wmem_default = 124928
    net.core.rmem_default = 124928
    net.core.rmem_max = 131071
    net.core.wmem_max = 131071
    net.core.netdev_max_backlog = 1000

    net.ipv4.tcp_rmem = 4096        87380   4194304
    net.ipv4.tcp_wmem = 4096        16384   4194304
    net.ipv4.tcp_window_scaling=1

You can change the current values of Linux configuration parameters by executing
these commands at a Linux prompt.  For example:

    # allow packet buffers to increase up to 64MB
    sudo /sbin/sysctl -w net.core.rmem_max=67108864
    sudo /sbin/sysctl -w net.core.wmem_max=67108864

    # increase the length of the processor input queue to 50,000
    sudo /sbin/sysctl -w net.core.netdev_max_backlog=50000

    # increase autotuning TCP buffer limit to 32MB
    sudo /sbin/sysctl -w net.ipv4.tcp_rmem=10240 87380 33554432
    sudo /sbin/sysctl -w net.ipv4.tcp_wmem=10240 87380 33554432

Changes to Linux configuration parameters with `/sbin/sysctl` persist only for the
current instance of Linux; they will revert to their default values when Linux
is rebooted. To change the default values used when Linux boots, specify them in
the Linux system file `/etc/sysctl.cfg`.

For more information, refer to [http://fasterdata.es.net/host-tuning/linux/].

# Threads

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator contains a separate thread for running `libpcap`,
which receives network packets from the operating system and produces tuples
from them.

The PacketLiveOperator contains a separate thread for reporting its metrics to
the Streams runtime if the `metricsInterval` parameter is greater than zero.

# Exceptions

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator will throw an exception and terminate in these
situations:

* The parameter 'networkInterface' does not specify a network interface defined on the machine where the operator executes.

* The 'inputFilter' and 'outputFilters' parameters do not specify a valid PCAP filter expression.

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

The ethernet frame format is described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethernet_frame]

The IPv4 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv4]
* [http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc791.txt]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/ip]

The IPv6 header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6_packet]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2460]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/ipv6]

The UDP header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_Datagram_Protocol]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc768]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/udp]

The TCP header and the fields it contains are described here:

* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transmission_Control_Protocol]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc793]
* [https://linux.die.net/man/7/tcp]

DNS messages and the fields they contain are described here:
  
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System]
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_DNS_record_types]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035]
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2308] for SOA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2872] for SRV resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3403] for NAPTR resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3596] for AAAA resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4034] for DS, RRSIG, NSEC, and DNSKEY resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4408] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5155] for NSEC3 and NSEC3PARAM resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6891] for OPT resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7208] for SPF resource records
* [http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7505] for MX resource records

The Juniper Networks 'jmirror' encapsulation header is described here:

* [http://wiki.wireshark.org/jmirror]

The Cisco Systems ''Encapsulated Remote Switch Port Analyzer (ERSPAN)' encapsulation headers are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-foschiano-erspan-00]

The 'Generic Route Encapsulation (GRE)' headers used by Cisco ERSPAN encapsulation are described here:

* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2784]
* [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1701]

Linux capabilities are described here:

* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/capabilities]

For more information about using Linux capabilities with Streams applications,
see:

* [http://www-01.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSCRJU_4.0.1/com.ibm.streams.install.doc/doc/ibminfospherestreams-install-programs-packages.html?lang=en]
* [http://www-01.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSCRJU_4.0.1/com.ibm.streams.cfg.doc/doc/creating-enterprise-domain.html?lang=en]
* [http://www-01.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSCRJU_4.0.1/com.ibm.streams.cfg.doc/doc/ibminfospherestreams-user-security-run-authority.html?lang=en]

`libpcap` filter expressions, 
which are used with the `inputFilter` parameter, are described here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|network header parser result functions].  

      </description>
      <metrics>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsReceivedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts the number of packets received by the network interface, 
as counted by `libpcap`

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsDroppedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts the number of packets dropped because there was no
room in the operating system's buffer when they arrived, as counted by
`libpcap`.

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nPacketsProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of packets processed by the operator.  When    
an input filter is specified, this includes only packets that pass the    
filter.

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
        <metric>
          <name>nBytesProcessedCurrent</name>
          <description>

This metric counts number of bytes of packet data processed by the
operator.  When an input filter is specified, this includes only packets
that pass the filter.

          </description>
          <kind>Counter</kind>
        </metric>
      </metrics>
      <customLiterals>
        <enumeration>
          <name>TimestampType</name>
          <value>host</value>
          <value>adapter</value>
          <value>adapter_unsynced</value>
        </enumeration>
      </customLiterals>
      <libraryDependencies>
        <library>
          <cmn:description> </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:command>../../impl/bin/libpcapPath.pl</cmn:command>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
        <library>
          <cmn:description> </cmn:description>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>
      </libraryDependencies>
      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
      <capability>CAP_NET_RAW+eip</capability>
      <capability>CAP_NET_ADMIN+eip</capability>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
      <parameter>
        <name>networkInterface</name>
        <description>

This required parameter takes an expression of type
`rstring` that specifies which network interface the operator will capture
packets from.  The value must be one of the network interface names
configured in Linux on the machine where the operator will execute.  To
display a list of configured network interface names, type this at a Linux
command prompt:

    /sbin/ifconfig

    </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>maximumLength</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `uint16`
that specifies the maximum length in bytes of the packet data that will be
produced by the operator.  This length includes all network headers;
packets longer than the specified length will be truncated.

The default value is 65,535 bytes.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint16</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>inputFilter</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `rstring`
that specifies which input packets should be processed. The value of this
string must be a valid PCAP filter expression, as defined here:

* [http://www.tcpdump.org/manpages/pcap-filter.7.html]
* [http://linux.die.net/man/7/pcap-filter]

The default value is 'udp port 53', which
causes only DNS packets received to be processed.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which packets
should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
of the
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.dns.html|DNSPacketLiveSource result functions].  

The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
causes all packets processed to be emitted by all output ports.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>promiscuous</name>
        <description>


This optional parameter takes an expression of type `boolean`
that specifies whether or not 'promiscuous' mode should be enabled on the
network interface.
If 'promiscious' mode is enabled, the
operator must execute with special Linux capabilities, as described above.

The default value is `false`.  However,
some values of the `inputFilter` parameter, including the default value,
require that 'promiscuous' mode be enabled on the network interface, even
if the `promiscous` parameter is not specified, or set to `false`.

    </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>initDelay</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `float64`
that specifies the number of seconds the operator will wait before it
begins to produce tuples.  This parameter is allowed only when the
`pcapFilename` parameter is also specified.

The default value is '0.0'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>bufferSize</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `uint32`
that specifies the size, in bytes, of the `libpcap` buffer used for
receiving packets.  The maximum value allowed is 2,147,483,647 (that is,
2\*\*31-1).

The default value of the `bufferSize` parameter is determined by `libpcap`.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>processorAffinity</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type
`uint32` that specifies which processor core the operator's thread will
run on.  The maximum value is *P-1*, where *P* is the number of processors
on the machine where the operator will run.  If this parameter is
specified, then the operator's thread will be dispatched only on the
specified processor.  

The default is to dispatch the operator's thread on any available processor.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>uint32</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>timeout</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type `float64` that
specifies a timeout for the `libpcap` interface.  If this value is
specified, the operator will call the `libpcap` interface again whenever
it times out, until the PE containing the operator receives a shutdown
signal.

The default is no timeout.  This may cause the thread that runs the
`libpcap` interface to hang on shutdown until another packet is received.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>timestampType</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes a value of 'host', 'adapter',
or 'adapter_unsynced', which specifies which type of timestamp will be
assigned to packets as they are received.

The default value is 'host'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>CustomLiteral</expressionMode>
        <type>TimestampType</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>

    <parameter>
      <name>jMirrorCheck</name>
      <description> 

This optional parameter takes an expression of type 'boolean'
that specifies whether or not the operator should check for Juniper Networks 'jMirror' headers on
packets, and step over them when found.

The default value is 'false'.

      </description>
      <optional>true</optional>
      <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
      <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
      <type>boolean</type>
      <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
    </parameter>

      <parameter>
        <name>metricsInterval</name>
        <description>

This optional parameter takes an expression of type
`float64` that specifies the interval, in seconds, for sending operator
metrics to the Streams runtime. If the value is zero or less, the operator
will not report metrics to the runtime, and the output assigment functions
for `libpcap` statistics will be zero.

The default value is '10.0'.

        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>float64</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts/>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>

The DNSPacketLiveSource operator requires one or more output ports:

Each output port will produce one output tuple for each packet received
(and passed by the input filter, if the `inputFilter` parameter is specified)
if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 

Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
[tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.source.html|DNSPacketLiveSource result functions].  
Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
type are copied automatically.

        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Generating</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>-1</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
