<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<operatorModel xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator" xmlns:cmn="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/operator operatorModel.xsd">
  <cppOperatorModel>
    <context>
      <description>

IPAddressLocation is an operator for the IBM Streams product that
finds the geographical location of IP addresses received in input tuples,
based on the subnets they are part of, and
emits output tuples containing the country, state or province, city, latitude, and longitude of the subnets.
The operator may be configured with one or more output ports,
and each port may be configured to emit different tuples,
as specified by output filters.

The IPAddressLocation operator consumes input tuples containing IP version 4 and 6 addresses,
selects messages to emit as output tuples with filter expressions,
and assigns values to them with output attribute assignment expressions.
Output filters and attribute assignments are SPL expressions. They may use any
of the built-in SPL functions, and any of these functions, which are specific to
the IPAddressLocation operator: 

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.location.html|location result functions]

The IPAddressLocation operator emits a tuple on each output port for each input tuple,
optionally filtered by the 'outputFilters'
parameter.  Geographical location data is assigned to output
attributes with the location result functions, based on the IP addresses specified with the functions.
All attributes of all output ports must be assigned values, either with explicit
assignment expressions, or implicitly by copy from input tuples.

This operator is part of the network toolkit. To use it in an application,
include this statement in the SPL source file:

    use com.ibm.streamsx.network.location::*;

# Dependencies

The IPAddressLocation operator depends upon geographical location data 
provided by [https://www.maxmind.com/|Maxmind, Inc.]:

* GeoLite2 data is available free from [https://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geolite2/]

* GeoIP2 data, which is more accurate, may be purchased from [https://www.maxmind.com/en/geoip2-city]

The required parameter `geographyDiectory` parameter must point to a directory containing
geography files, after downloading and unpacking. 

For GeoLite2 data, the geography files are:

    GeoLite2-City-Locations-en.csv
    GeoLite2-City-Blocks-IPv4.csv   
    GeoLite2-City-Blocks-IPv6.csv

For GeoIP2 data, the geography files are:

    GeoIP2-City-Locations-en.csv
    GeoIP2-City-Blocks-IPv4.csv   
    GeoIP2-City-Blocks-IPv6.csv

The format of the geography files is described here:

* [https://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geoip2-city-country-csv-databases/]

# Threads

The IPAddressLocation runs on the thread of the upstream operator that sends
input tuples to it. It does not start any threads of its own.

# Exceptions

The IPAddressLocation operator will throw an exception and terminate in these
situations:

* No output ports are specified.

* The `outputFilters` parameter is specified, and the number of expressions 
specified does not match the number of output ports specified.

# Sample Applications

The network toolkit includes several
[https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.network/tree/master/samples|sample applications]
that illustrate how to use this operator.

# References

The result functions that can be used in boolean
expressions for the `outputFilters` parameter
and in output attribute assignment expressions are described here:

* [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.location.html|location result functions].  

The format of the GeoIP2 and GeoLite2 CSV files provided by [https://www.maxmind.com/|Maxmind, Inc.] is described here:

* [https://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geoip2-city-country-csv-databases/]

The format of 'geohash' codes for latitude and longitude coordinates is described here:

* [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geohash]

      </description>

      <libraryDependencies>

        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_boost_filesystem</cmn:lib>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_boost_system</cmn:lib>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:lib>streams_boost_regex</cmn:lib>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

        <library>
          <cmn:description/>
          <cmn:managedLibrary>
            <cmn:includePath>../../impl/include</cmn:includePath>
          </cmn:managedLibrary>
        </library>

      </libraryDependencies>

      <providesSingleThreadedContext>Always</providesSingleThreadedContext>
      <allowCustomLogic>true</allowCustomLogic>
    </context>
    <parameters>
      <description></description>
      <allowAny>false</allowAny>
      <parameter>
        <name>geographyDirectory</name>
        <description>
          This required parameter specifies a directory containing GeoIP2 or GeoLite2 files
          downloaded from [http://www.maxmind.com|MaxMind, Inc.] 
        </description>
        <optional>false</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>AttributeFree</expressionMode>
        <type>rstring</type>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
      <parameter>
        <name>outputFilters</name>
        <description>
          This optional parameter takes a list of SPL expressions that specify which input tuples
          should be emitted by the corresponding output port. The number of
          expressions in the list must match the number of output ports, and each
          expression must evaluate to a `boolean` value.  The output filter expressions may include any
          of the
          [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.location.html|location result functions].  
          
          The default value of the `outputFilters` parameter is an empty list, which
          causes each input tuple to be emitted by all output ports.
        </description>
        <optional>true</optional>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <type>boolean</type>
        <cardinality>-1</cardinality>
      </parameter>
    </parameters>
    <inputPorts>
      <inputPortSet>
        <description>
          The IPAddressLocation operator requires one input port. One or more input attributes
          must be of type `uint32` or `list&lt;uint8>\[16\]` containing IP version 4 or 6 addresses, respectively.
          These attributes are specified as arguments to the location result functions.
        </description>
        <windowingDescription></windowingDescription>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <windowingMode>NonWindowed</windowingMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputMode>Oblivious</windowPunctuationInputMode>
        <cardinality>1</cardinality>
        <optional>false</optional>
      </inputPortSet>
    </inputPorts>
    <outputPorts>
      <outputPortOpenSet>
        <description>
          The IPAddressLocation operator requires one or more output ports.
          
          Each output port will produce one output tuple for each input tuple
          if the corresponding expression in the `outputFilters` parameter evaluates `true`,
          or if no `outputFilters` parameter is specified. 
          
          Output attributes can be assigned values with any SPL expression that evaluates
          to the proper type, and the expressions may include any of the 
          [tk$com.ibm.streamsx.network/fc$com.ibm.streamsx.network.location.html|location result functions].  
          Output attributes that match input attributes in name and
          type are copied automatically.
        </description>
        <expressionMode>Expression</expressionMode>
        <autoAssignment>false</autoAssignment>
        <completeAssignment>false</completeAssignment>
        <rewriteAllowed>true</rewriteAllowed>
        <windowPunctuationOutputMode>Preserving</windowPunctuationOutputMode>
        <windowPunctuationInputPort>0</windowPunctuationInputPort>
        <tupleMutationAllowed>false</tupleMutationAllowed>
        <allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>true</allowNestedCustomOutputFunctions>
      </outputPortOpenSet>
    </outputPorts>
  </cppOperatorModel>
</operatorModel>
